Fellow citizens,
in obedience to the will of the people,
and in their presence by the authority
vested in me by this oath I assume
the arduous and responsible duties
of President of the United States.
Relying upon the support of my countrymen,
and invoking the guidance of Almighty God,
our faith teaches that there is no safer
reliance than upon the God
of our fathers who has
so singularly favored the American
people in every national trial
and who will not forsake us
so long as we obey his commandments
and walk humbly in his footsteps the respo
nsibilities of the high trust to which I
have been called always of grave importanc
e are augmented by the prevailing business
conditions entailing idleness upon willing
labor and loss to useful enterprises.
The country is suffering from industrial
disturbances from which speedy relief must
be had our financial
system needs some revision.
Our money is all good now, but its
value must not further be threatened.
It should all be put upon an enduring
basis, not subject to easy attack,
nor its stability to doubt or dispute.
Our currency should continue under the
supervision of the government the several
forms of our paper money offer
in my judgment a constant embarrassment
to the government
and a safe balance in the Treasury.
Therefore, I believe it necessary to
devise a system which, without diminishing
the circulating medium or offering
a premium for its contraction will present
a remedy for those arrangements
which temporary in their nature might.
Well in the years of our prosperity
have been displaced by wiser provisions
with adequate revenue secured, but not
until then we can enter upon such changes
in our fiscal laws as will while insuring
safety and volume to our money no longer
impose upon the government
the necessity of maintaining
so large a gold reserve with its attendant
and inevitable temptations to speculation
most of our financial laws
are the outgrowth of experience and trial
and should not
be amended without investigation
and demonstration of the wisdom of the
proposed changes, we must be both sure.
We are right and make
haste slowly if therefore, Congress,
in its wisdom shall deem it expedient
to create a Commission to take under early
consideration.
The revision of our coinage banking
and currency laws
and give them that exhaustive careful
and dispassionate examination
that their importance demands.
I shall cordially concur in such action.
If such power is vested in the President.
It is my purpose to appoint a Commission
of prominent well-informed citizens
of different parties,
who will command public confidence,
both on account of their ability
and special fitness for the work business
experience,
and public training may thus be combined
and the patriotic zeal of the friends
of the country be so directed that such
a report will be made
as to receive the support of all parties
and our finances cease to be the subject
of mere partisan contention.
The experiment is at all events
worth a trial and in my opinion,
it can but prove
beneficial to the entire country.
The question of international bimetallism
will have early and earnest attention.
It will be my constant endeavor to secure
it by co-operation with the other great
commercial powers of the world
until that condition is realized
when the parity between our gold and
silver money springs from and is supported
by the relative value of the two metals.
The value of the silver already coined
and of that which may hereafter be coined
must be kept constantly at par with gold
by every resource at our command,
the credit of the government.
The integrity of its currency, and
the inviolability of its obligations must
be preserved.
This was the commanding verdict of the peo
ple, and it will not be unheeded economy
is demanded in every
branch of the government.
At all times, but especially in periods li
ke the present of depression in business,
and distress among the people.
The severest economy must
be observed in all public expenditures,
and extravagance stopped
wherever it is found,
and prevented wherever in the future,
it may be developed if the revenues
are to remain as now, the only relief
that can come must be from decreased
expenditures.
But the present must not become
the permanent condition of the government.
It has been our
uniform practice to retire,
not increase our outstanding obligations,
and this policy must again be resumed
and vigorously enforced our revenues shoul
d always be large enough to meet with ease
and promptness, not only our current needs
and the principal
and interest of the public debt,
but to make proper
and liberal provision for that most
deserving body of public creditors.
The soldiers and sailors and the widows
and orphans who are the pensioners
of the United States.
The government should not be permitted to
run behind or increase its debt in times
like the present suitably to provide again
st this is the mandate of duty the certain
and easy remedy
for most of our financial difficulties.
A deficiency is inevitable.
So long as the expenditures
of the government exceed its receipts.
It can only be met
by loans or an increased revenue,
while a large annual surplus
of revenue may invite waste,
and extravagance inadequate revenue
creates distrust and undermines,
public and private credit.
Neither should be encouraged between
more loans and more revenue,
there ought to be, but one opinion,
we should have more revenue
and that without delay hindrance or postpo
nement a surplus in the Treasury created
by loans is not
a permanent or safe reliance.
It will suffice while it lasts,
but it can not last long
while the outlays of the government
are greater than its receipts as has been
the case.
During the past two years, nor must it be
forgotten that however much such loans may
temporarily relieve the situation the gove
rnment is still indebted for the amount
of the surplus thus accrued
which it must ultimately pay
while its ability
to pay is not strengthened,
but weakened by a continued deficit
loans are imperative in great emergencies
to preserve the government or its credit.
But a failure to supply needed revenue.
In time of peace, for the maintenance of
either has no justification the best way
for the government to maintain its
credit is to pay as it goes,
not by resorting to loans, but by keeping
out of debt through an adequate income
secured by a system
of taxation external or internal or both.
It is the settled policy of the government
pursued from the beginning
and practiced by all parties and administr
ations to raise the bulk of our revenue
from taxes upon foreign productions
entering the United States for sale
and consumption
and avoiding for the most part,
every form of direct taxation
except in time of war.
The country is clearly opposed to any need
less additions to the subject of internal
taxation, and is committed by its latest
popular utterance to the system of tariff
taxation there can be no misunderstanding,
either about the principle upon which this
tariff taxation shall be levied nothing
has ever been made plainer at a general el
ection than that the controlling principle
in the raising of revenue from duties
on imports is zealous care for American
interests and American labor.
The people have declared that such legisla
tion should be had as will give ample
protection and encouragement to the indust
ries and the development of our country.
It is therefore earnestly hoped and expect
ed that Congress will at the earliest
practicable moment enact revenue
legislation that shall be fair reasonable
conservative and just and which while
supplying sufficient revenue for public
purposes will still be signally beneficial
and helpful to every section
and every enterprise
of the people to this policy,
we are all of whatever party firmly
bound by the voice of the people,
a power vastly more potential than
the expression of any political platform.
The paramount duty of Congress
is to stop deficiencies by the restoration
of that protective legislation,
which has always been the firmest prop
of the Treasury.
The passage of such a law or laws would
strengthen the credit of the government,
both at home and abroad, and go far toward
stopping the drain upon the gold reserve
held for the redemption of our currency
which has been heavy
and well-nigh constant for several years
in the revision of the tariff especial
attention should
be given to the re-enactment
and extension of the reciprocity principle
of the law of 1890 under
which so great a stimulus
was given to our foreign trade in new
and advantageous markets for our surplus
agricultural and manufactured products,
the brief trial given this legislation
amply justifies a further experiment
and additional discretionary power in the
making of commercial treaties the end
in view always to be the opening up of new
markets for the products of our country
by granting concessions to the products
of other lands that we need
and cannot produce ourselves and which do
not involve any loss of labor to our own
people.
But tend to increase their employment.
The depression of the past four years
has fallen with especial severity upon
the great body of toilers of the country,
and upon none more than the holders
of small farms.
Agriculture has languished and labor
suffered the revival of manufacturing will
be a relief to both no portion of our popu
lation is more devoted to the institution
of free government,
nor more loyal in their support,
while none bears more cheerfully or fully
its proper share in the maintenance
of the government or is better
entitled to its wise and liberal care
and protection legislation helpful to prod
ucers is beneficial to all the depressed
condition of industry on the farm,
and in the mine,
and factory has lessened the ability of
the people to meet the demands upon them
and they rightfully expect that not only
a system of revenue shall be established
that will secure the largest
income with the least burden,
but that every means will be taken to
decrease rather than increase our public
expenditures business conditions are not
the most promising it will take time
to restore the prosperity of former years,
if we cannot promptly attain it.
We can resolutely turn
our faces in that direction
and aid its
return by friendly legislation.
However, troublesome the situation may app
ear Congress will not I am sure be found
lacking in disposition or ability to relie
ve it as far as legislation can do so.
The restoration of confidence and the revi
val of business which men of all parties
so much desire depend,
more largely upon the prompt energetic
and intelligent action of Congress than
upon any other single agency affecting
the situation, it is inspiring too to reme
mber that no great emergency in the one
hundred and eight years of our eventful
national life has ever arisen that has not
been met with wisdom and courage by the Am
erican people with fidelity to their best
interests and highest destiny
and to the honor of the American name.
These years of glorious
history have exalted mankind
and advanced the cause
of freedom throughout the world,
and immeasurably strengthened.
The precious free institutions
which we enjoy the people love
and will sustain these institutions
the great essential to our happiness
and prosperity is that we
adhere to the principles upon
which the government was established
and insist upon their faithful
observance equality of rights must prevail
and our laws be always and everywhere,
respected and obeyed.
We may have failed in the discharge
of our full duty as citizens of the great
Republic.
But it is consoling and encouraging
to realize that free speech a free press,
free thought free schools, the free
and unmolested right of religious liberty
and worship and free
and fair elections are dearer
and more universally enjoyed
to-day than ever before.
These guaranties must be sacredly
preserved, and wisely strengthened.
The constituted authorities
must be cheerfully
and vigorously upheld lynchings must
not be tolerated in a great
and civilized country,
like the United States courts,
not mobs must execute
the penalties of the law.
The preservation of public order,
the right of discussion.
The integrity of courts, and the orderly
administration of justice must continue
forever.
The rock of safety upon which our governme
nt securely rests one of the lessons
taught by the late election,
which all can rejoice.
In is that the citizens of the United
States are both law-respecting
and law-abiding people, not easily swerved
from the path of patriotism, and honor.
This is in entire accord
with the genius of our institutions
and but emphasizes the advantages
of inculcating even a greater love for law
and order in the future immunity should
be granted to none who violate the laws
whether individuals
corporations or communities,
and, as the Constitution
imposes upon the President,
the duty of both its own execution.
And of the statutes enacted
in pursuance of its provisions.
I shall endeavor carefully
to carry them into effect.
The Declaration of the party now restored
to power has been in the past
that of opposition to all combinations of
capital organized in trusts or otherwise
to control arbitrarily.
The condition of trade among our citizens,
and it has supported such legislation
as will prevent the execution of all schem
es to oppress the people by undue charges
on their supplies or by unjust rates
for the transportation of their products
to the market.
This purpose will be steadily pursued both
by the enforcement of the laws now
in existence and the recommendation
and support of such new statutes as may
be necessary to carry it into effect.
Our naturalization and immigration laws
should be further improved to the constant
promotion of a safer,
a better and a higher citizenship.
A grave peril to the Republic would be
a citizenship too ignorant to understand
or too vicious to appreciate the great
value and beneficence of our institutions
and laws and against all who come here
to make war upon them our gates must
be promptly and tightly closed.
Nor must we be unmindful of the need
of improvement among our own citizens,
but with the zeal of our forefathers,
encourage the spread of knowledge
and free education illiteracy must
be banished from the land.
If we shall attain that high destiny.
As the foremost of the enlightened
nations of the world
which under Providence we ought to achieve
reforms in the civil service must go on.
But the changes should be real and genuine
, not perfunctory or prompted by a zeal
in behalf of any party simply because it
happens to be in power as a member
of Congress I voted
and spoke in favor of the present law
and I shall attempt its enforcement
in the spirit in which it was enacted
the purpose.
In view was to secure the most efficient
service of the best men who would accept
appointment under
the government retaining faithful
and devoted public servants in office, but
shielding none under the authority of any
rule or custom who are inefficient
incompetent or unworthy the best interests
of the country demand this and the people
heartily approve the law wherever
and whenever it has been thus administrate
d Congress should give prompt attention
to the restoration of our American merchan
t Marine once the pride of the seas in all
the great ocean highways of commerce
to my mind few more important subjects.
So imperatively demand
its intelligent consideration.
The United States has progressed
with marvelous rapidity in every field
of enterprise and endeavor until we have
become foremost in nearly all the great
lines of inland trade commerce
and industry.
Yet while this is true our American mercha
nt Marine has been steadily declining
until it is now lower
both in the percentage of tonnage
and the number of vessels employed than
it was prior to the civil war commendable
progress has been made of late years.
In the upbuilding of the American Navy.
But we must supplement these efforts
by providing as a proper consort for it,
a merchant Marine amply sufficient for our
own carrying trade to foreign countries.
The question is one that appeals
both to our business necessities
and the patriotic aspirations
of a great people.
It has been
the policy of the United States.
Since the foundation of the government
to cultivate relations of peace
and amity with all the nations of the
world, and this accords with my conception
of our duty.
Now we have cherished the policy of
non-interference with affairs of foreign
governments wisely
inaugurated by Washington.
Keeping ourselves free from entanglement
either as allies or foes content to leave
undisturbed with them the settlement
of their own domestic concerns.
It will be our aim to pursue a firm
and dignified foreign policy
which shall be just impartial
ever watchful of our national honor
and always insisting upon the enforcement
of the lawful rights of American citizens
everywhere.
Our diplomacy should seek nothing more
and accept nothing less than is due us.
We want no wars of conquest.
We must avoid
the temptation of territorial aggression.
War should never be entered
upon until every agency of peace,
has failed peace is preferable
to war in almost every contingency.
Arbitration is the true method of settleme
nt of international as well as local
or individual differences.
It was recognized as the best means of adj
ustment of differences between employers
and employees by the forty-ninth
Congress in 1886
and its application was extended to our
diplomatic relations by the unanimous
concurrence of the Senate and House
of the fifty-first Congress in 1890,
the latter resolution was accepted
as the basis of negotiations with us
by the British House of commons in 1893
and upon our invitation a treaty
of arbitration between the United States
and great Britain was signed at Washington
and transmitted to the Senate
for its ratification.
In January.
Last since this treaty is clearly
the result of our own initiative,
since it has been recognized as the leadin
g feature of our foreign policy throughout
our entire history.
The adjustment of difficulties by judicial
methods rather than force of arms
and since it presents to the world.
The glorious example of reason and peace,
not passion and war controlling the relati
ons between two of the greatest nations
in the world, an example
certain to be followed by others.
I respectfully urge the early action of
the Senate thereon not merely as a matter
of policy.
But as a duty to mankind the importance
and moral influence of the ratification
of such a treaty can hardly be overestimat
ed in the cause of advancing civilization.
It may well engage the best thought of
the statesmen and people of every country
and I cannot but consider it fortunate
that it was reserved to the United States
to have the leadership in so grand a work
it has been the uniform practice of each
President to avoid as far as possible
the convening of Congress in extraordinary
session.
It is an example which under ordinary circ
umstances and in the absence of a public
necessity is to be commended.
But a failure to convene the representativ
es of the people in Congress in extra
session when, it involves neglect of a pub
lic duty places the responsibility of such
neglect upon the Executive himself
the condition of the public Treasury.
As has been indicated demands.
The immediate consideration of Congress.
It alone has the power
to provide revenues for the government,
not to convene
it under such circumstances.
I can view in no other sense
than the neglect of a plain duty.
I do not sympathize with the sentiment tha
t Congress in session is dangerous to our
general business interests.
Its members are the agents of the people,
and their presence at the seat
of government in the execution
of the sovereign will should not operate
as an injury, but a benefit there could be
no better time to put the government upon
a sound financial
and economic basis than now.
The people have only recently
voted that this should be done.
And nothing is more binding upon the
agents of their will than the obligation
of immediate action.
It has always seemed to me that the postpo
nement of the meeting of Congress until
more than a year.
After it has been chosen deprived.
Congress, too often of the inspiration
of the popular will
and the country
of the corresponding benefits.
It is evident, therefore, that to postpone
action in the presence of so great
a necessity would be unwise
on the part of the Executive
because unjust to the interests
of the people.
Our action now will be freer from mere par
tisan consideration than if the question
of tariff revision was postponed
until the regular session of Congress,
we are nearly two
years from a congressional election,
and politics cannot so greatly distract
us as if such contest was immediately
pending.
We can approach the problem calmly and pat
riotically without fearing its effect upon
an early election.
Our fellow-citizens who may disagree with
us upon the character of this legislation
prefer to have the question settled now,
even against their preconceived views and
perhaps settled so reasonably as I trust,
and believe it will be as to insure
great permanence than to have further
uncertainty menacing the vast and varied
business interests of the United States
again.
Whatever action Congress may take will be
given a fair opportunity for trial before
the people are called to pass judgment upo
n it and this I consider a great essential
to the rightful and lasting settlement
of the question in view of these
considerations, I shall deem it my
duty as President to convene Congress
in extraordinary session on Monday.
The 15th day of march 1897.
In conclusion I congratulate the country
upon the fraternal spirit of the people
and the manifestations
of good will everywhere
so apparent the recent election
not only most fortunately demonstrated
the obliteration
of sectional or geographical lines,
but to some extent also the prejudices whi
ch for years have distracted our councils
and marred our true greatness.
As a nation, the triumph of the people.
Whose verdict is carried into effect.
Today is not the triumph of one section,
nor wholly of one party,
but of all sections and all the people
the North and the South no longer divide
on the old lines, but upon principles
and policies and in this fact,
surely every lover of the country
can find cause for true felicitation.
Let us rejoice
in and cultivate this spirit.
It is ennobling and will be both a gain
and a blessing to our beloved country,
it will be my constant aim to do nothing,
and permit nothing to be done that will
arrest or disturb this growing
sentiment of unity and cooperation.
This revival of esteem
and affiliation which now animates
so many thousands
in both the old antagonistic sections.
But I shall cheerfully do everything
possible to promote and increase it.
Let me again repeat the words of the oath
administered by the Chief justice
which in their respective spheres,
so far as applicable.
I would have all my countrymen, observe,
I will faithfully execute the office
of President of the United States and will
to the best of my ability preserve,
protect, and defend
the Constitution of the United States.
This is the obligation I have reverently
taken before the Lord most high to keep it
will be my single purpose my constant
prayer and I shall confidently rely upon
the forbearance and assistance of all
the people in the discharge of my solemn
responsibilities.